A Guide to the Shenandoah Valley Bicycle Coalition Records, 1983-2016: SC 0230
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Shenandoah Valley Bicycle Coalition Records,
1983-2016
Special Collections, James Madison University
Shenandoah Valley Bicycle Coalition
SC 0230
.8 cubic feet; 2 boxes
The Shenandoah Valley Bicycle Coalition Records, 1983-2016, document the activities of the Shenandoah Valley Bicycle Coalition (SVBC), formerly named the Shenandoah Valley Bicycle Club. Materials include newsletters, meeting minutes, correspondence, and promotional material and route maps for the Annual Shenandoah Valley Century Ride.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated by SVBC members Art Fovargue and Marshall Hammond on January 30, 2017. They delivered the materials to Carrier Library on bicycle.
Other Formats Available
A digital version of the full run of SVBC newsletters is available at: http://svbcoalition.org/newsletters/archives/. A digital version of SVBC board meeting minutes and monthly social minutes is available at: http://svbcoalition.org/meeting-minutes/.
Administrative History
The Shenandoah Valley Bicycle Coalition (SVBC), formerly the Shenandoah Valley Bicycle Club, formed in December 1982 as a road cycling club. The idea of forming a local bicycle club had been in the works since 1981 and after James Fulton, President of the League of American Wheelman, visited the Shenandoah Valley in December 1982, it was decided that the Valley was ready to play a more active role in the in the growing sport of bicycling. The club was founded with the basic purpose of providing "opportunities for extending the individuals knowledge and appreciation of his/her environment and abilities through the experience in bicycling." The founding officers were Mark Nissley, President; Bruce Werner, Vice President; Ray Miller, Secretary and L.A.W. Representative; Sue Rippy, Treasurer; Norm Gulliksen, Touring Director; and L. B. Branner, Newsletter Editor.
The Shenandoah Valley Bicycle Coalition hosts weekly, monthly, and annual rides with the most noted and longest running being the annual Shenandoah Valley Century, a 100-mile bicycle ride. This annual ride began in 1983 and takes place in September, coinciding with National Century Month. Rides of various lengths are offered at this event to accommodate all abilities and skillsets. Other SVBC-sponsored rides of note include the Annual Icicle Bike Ride (January 1), the Annual Super Bowl Sunday Ride, and the Annual Great Valley Interstate Tour from Harrisburg (PA) to Harrisonburg (VA) (AGVITHH). The starting location and final destination of AGVITHH rotated every year.
In 2008, the Shenandoah Valley Bicycle Club merged with the Shenandoah Valley Mountain Bike Club (founded in 1996) to form the Shenandoah Valley Bicycle Coalition.
Scope and Content
The Shenandoah Valley Bicycle Coalition Records, 1983-2016, document the activities of the Shenandoah Valley Bicycle Coalition, formerly named the Shenandoah Valley Bicycle Club. Materials include newsletters, meeting minutes, correspondence, and promotional material and route maps for the Annual Shenandoah Valley Century Ride. The collection is arranged in three series: Newsletters, Administrative Files, and Ride Materials.
Series 1: Newsletters, 1983-2008, comprises exclusively newsletters produced by the Shenandoah Valley Bicycle Coalition. The first issue of the SVBC newsletter was issued in March 1983. This series includes a full run of newsletters beginning with the inaugural issue through 2006 with the exception of the following missing newsletters: December 1988, January 1991, April-July 1995, January/February-March 1996, April-May 1998, May 2004, and August 2005. From there after, only the January/February 2007 and April 2008 issues are present. As of April 2008, the newsletter adopted the name The Mellow Vélo, after the French translation of bicycle. The newsletters were issued monthly or bi-monthly and provided news stories, a calendar of upcoming meetings and events, member news, classifieds, information on rides, and general happenings within the SVBC.
Series 2: Administrative Files, 1983-2006, contains scattered SVBC organizational records and includes handwritten meeting minutes, SVBC's 1992 Constitution and Bylaws, awards and certificates, correspondence, and treasurer's reports. Several Adopt-A-Highway Certificates of Appreciation are included as is a copy of the May 1999 Certificate of Recognition of Bicycle Month by the Commonwealth of Virginia. The correspondence is primarily thank-you cards and letters for donations made by SVBC to local organizations and scholarship funds.
Series 3: Ride Materials, 1983-2016, includes documents relating to the Shenandoah Valley Century Ride including posters, route maps and cue sheets, and brochures.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 3 series:
Series 1: Newsletters, 1983-2008
Series 2: Administrative Files, 1983-2006 Series 3: Ride Materials, 1983-2016
All series are arranged chronologically.
Bibliography
Shenandoah Valley Bicycle Coalition. http://svbcoalition.org. Accessed May 8, 2017.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Bicycles -- Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.); Cycling -- Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.); Athletic clubs -- Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.); Sports -- Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- History; Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- History; Virginia -- History, Local
Genre and Form Terms:
Newsletters; Letters (correspondence); Maps (documents); Minutes (administrative records); Awards; Certificates; Administrative reports; Brochures; Constitutions; Bylaws (administrative records); Posters
- Series 1: Newsletters, 1983-2008
  - Newsletters, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Newsletters, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Newsletters, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newsletters, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Newsletters, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Newsletters, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Newsletters, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Newsletters, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Newsletters, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Newsletters, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Newsletters, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Newsletters, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Newsletters, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Newsletters, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Newsletters, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Newsletters, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Newsletters, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Newsletters, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series 2: Administrative Files, 1983-2006
  - Meeting Minutes, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Constitution and Bylaws, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1999-2004 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 2001-2006, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 2005-2006 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Series 3: Ride Materials, 1983-2016
  - Shenandoah Valley Century Posters, 1983-2016 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Shenandoah Valley Century Route Maps (Masters), 1984-2016 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Shenandoah Valley Century Brochures, 1995-2016 (Box 2, Folder 19)